Departure
[The future is in my hands]
さあ　はった　はった
Come, place your bets!
来い
Come on...
来い！
Come on!
かーっ　クソ！
Darn it!
[The future is in my hands]
東京に来て３年
Three years since coming to Tokyo,
伊藤開司は最悪だった
Ito Kaiji was the pits.
正月が明けてから
１日も働いていない
He had not worked a day since the new year.
しょぼい酒としょぼい博打の日々
His days are filled with cheap booze and gambling.
そして　そんな鬱憤を
晴らすために…
And to release his pent up frustrations...
クソッ
Darn it!
だが　この日
彼がひいきにしている外車が
But today, he could not find an imported car he liked.
見つからなかった
今日はこれで我慢するか
Shall I just make do with this then?
どうせ　こんな車に
乗ってる奴なんか
No decent chap would drive something like this anyway.
ろくな奴じゃ…
金か…　金だよな
Money, huh?
It's all about money! Money...
金…
だから泣いてどうすんだよ
俺は…
But what's the use of crying?
I'm a fool! Darn it...
アホか　クソッ
何だよ　おら！
What is it?!
あ…　何でしょうか？
What can I do for you?
きみ　伊藤カイジ君？
Are you Ito Kaiji?
はあ　そうですが
Yeah, that's me.
古畑武志　知ってるよね？
古畑？
Do you know Furuhata Takeshi?
Furuhata?
ああ　確か１年くらい前バイトで
でも今は…
Yeah, we worked part-time together a year ago, but now...
中でいいかな？戸口で
話すようなことじゃないんだ
Can we talk inside?
This is not something to be discussed in the doorway.
えっ？いや　それはちょっと…
What? N-No, that's...
やべえ　壁のエンブレム
Oh, no! The emblems on the wall!
あ　あの…　外　行きませんか？
お茶とか
Um... Why don't we go outside?
For a cup of tea?
かまわんよ　じゃあ　車を回そう
Sounds fine. Let's take my car.
あ　はい
O-Okay.
何だ？何か知らんけど
ともかく隠しておこう
What's going on?
Whatever it is, I'd better hide these.
ついてねえよ　カイジ君
はい？
You're out of luck, Kaiji.
- What? - My car's got a puncture.
車　パンクしちまった
迎えが来るまで待ちだ
中　入るか？
We'll have to wait for someone to pick us up.
Want to go in?
えっ？そ…　そんなに
寒くないですし
What? I-It's not that cold anyway...
そうじゃない
目立ちたくねえんだ
It's not that.
I don't want to draw attention.
Y-Yeah.
どうぞ
すまんな
- Please. - Sorry about that.
No problem.
Yeah, but honestly, lots of punks out there...
しかし世の中には　たちの悪い
イタズラする奴がいますよね
...have gone too far with their pranks, eh?
ったく　何考えてんだか
What the heck are they thinking, anyway?
お前か
Was it you?
な…　何言ってんですか
いきなり
What are you implying, out of the blue?!
俺はパンクしたと言っただけで
I only said that the car's got a puncture.
イタズラされたとは言ってない
I never said that anyone punctured it.
あ… いや…
No, w-wait a minute!
ちょ ちょっと… うわっ
Uh, no... This is, what do you call it...
あ… いや これは その
何と言うか…
ごめんなさい
見てのとおりなんです
I'm sorry! It is as you see!
I only specialise in cars with this emblem, not others!
俺 このｴﾝﾌﾞﾚﾑの車 専門でして
ほかの車には…
お前 なぜ俺の車が
そのｴﾝﾌﾞﾚﾑのじゃないと知ってる？
Hey, how did you know that my car isn't of that emblem?
え？あ…
墓穴　ダブルで墓穴
ダブボケ
I dug my own grave.
A double grave. Doubly stupid.
あの 弁償
どれぐらいになるんでしょうか？
Excuse me... How much are the repairs?
いいよ
はい？
- Forget it. - What?
お前から金取る手間ひま
考えたら
If I have time to fleece you of money,
板金屋の親父 脅したほうが早い
I'd get it faster from the old man at the auto shop.
第一 お前は今
それどころじゃないんだ
Besides, you have more to worry about.
古畑君だよ
What?
It's about Furuhata.
え？あいつ
消えちゃったんですか？
Huh? H-He's disappeared?
Yeah. And he left behind a trail of debts.
ああ 後に残されたのは
サラ金から借りまくった借金
その１つがこれだ
覚えてるか？
This is one of them.
Do you remember this?
あの野郎…
That scum!
先輩 助けてください
どうしても金がいるんです
Senior, please help me!
I really need the money. I beg of you!
お願いします
迷惑かけませんから保証人に…
I won't give you trouble, just be my guarantor!
クソッ
Darn it!
思い出したかな カイジ君
So you do remember, Kaiji?
当人が消えちまった以上
With the debtor gone,
この債務は保証人のお前が
払うことになる
you'll have to pay this debt as his guarantor.
でも俺 金ないし とても…
But I have no money at all...
月々 少しずつでいいんだ
Just pay by small monthly instalments.
少しずつったって
30万も返すとなったら…
Even so, it's a sum of 300,000 yen...
またまた冗談言って
Are you kidding me?!
Loans come with interests.
借りた金には金利ってのが
つくんだよ
30万ってわけないでしょ
It can't just be 300,000 yen.
What?
古畑は１円も払わずドロンした
ここを見ろ
Furuhata vanished without paying a single cent.
Look at this.
月20％の複利ってあるだろ
There's a 20% compound interest, right?
この金利で14ヵ月
転がったことになる
This interest has been accumulating for 14 months.
30万程度じゃ とてもとても…
300,000 yen would definitely not cover it!
じゃ いくらなんですか？
So, how much is it?
3,850,000 yen.
385万
さ… さんびゃく？
T-Three million...?!
This is a simple compound interest chart, Mr. Kaiji.
これが複利の早見表だ カイジ君
N-No way!
こ こんなバカな…
20％だと そうなるんだよ
At 20%, that's how it works.
こうなったら
コツコツ返すしかねえな
At this state, you can hope to pay it back in small amounts.
だが安心しな
But don't worry.
もう こんなバカな金利は
外してやる
I will get rid of this absurd rate.
良心的なとこで月々10万…
いや 10は無理か
Out of good will, 100,000 yen a month...
Wait, 100,000 is too much?
In that case, 60,000! 60,000 at least...
じゃあ６… ６は払わんとな
これで年利15％の元利均等返済
At an annual interest rate of 15%,
you can pay off the principal and interest evenly.
385万返済するのに
To pay off 3,850,000 yen, it would take...
約130ヵ月 11年
...about 130 months, or 11 years.
思ったより短いじゃないか
It's sooner than I thought!
額に汗して働けば
32～3歳で全額 返済だ
If you work hard, you'd be able to clear the debt...
...at around 32 or 33 years of age.
なあ？
ふざけろ
Well?
Don't mess with me! I'll never pay!
俺は絶対 払わないからな
第一 こんな暴利 違法だろう
Anyway, this loan-shark business is illegal!
カイジ君　違法も法だよ
Mr. Kaiji, illegal business is a law in itself.
We are professionals and will do anything to reclaim the debt.
俺たちはプロだから
どんなことをしてでも取り立てる
カイジ君のお姉さん
公務員だったよな？
Your sister's a civil servant, isn't she?
それに父親はいないが
And though your father has passed on,
おふくろさんはまだ元気で
パートで働いてる
you mother is still healthy and working part-time.
き 貴様…
Y-You!
カイジ
Kaiji!
本意じゃねえ
本意じゃねえんだ 俺だって
I didn't intend for this. I don't want to do it either.
I don't want to see a family squabbling over such a matter.
家族でののしり合うさまを
俺だって見たかねえ
座れ　本題に入ろう
Sit down. Let's discuss the main topic.
本題？
そうだ
- Main topic? - That's right.
これから話すことが俺の本意
What I'm about to say is my real intention.
A cruise ship will depart from Harumi pier in a month from now.
１ヵ月後に晴海埠頭から船が出る
今 この船に乗る参加者を募ってる
I am currently recruiting people to board it.
その船でひと晩 うまくしのげば
If all goes well, a night on that ship...
...will clear your debts once and for all.
お前の借金は全部 チャラになる
えっ チャラ？
その上
Huh? Once and for all?
Also, an additional profit of 10 or 20 million yen is possible.
1000万 2000万
儲けることも可能だ
そ それって…
ギャンブルだよ
T-That's...
It's gambling.
お前のような
行き詰まった負債者を集めて
It's gathering people like you who are...
ひと晩だけ
ギャンブルをしてもらう
...burdened with debts for a night of gambling.
その船で負ければ
さらに借金を背負い込み
Those who lose will sink deeper in debt,
and be brought to do forced labour for a year or two.
某所に連れていかれ
最低でも１～２年 強制労働
シャバには戻れない
You won't be able to return to society.
だが大金をつかんで
船を下りる奴も
But there are always some who leave the ship...
毎回 何人もいる
...with a fortune on their hands.
Kaiji, you shall board this ship!
カイジ　お前 これに乗れ
乗ってしのいで
きれいになって帰ってこい
Board it, survive and return clean as a sheet!
か… 勝てばチャラ？
If I win, my debts are cleared?
Yeah.
お前のようなクズの最終戦
It's the last battle for scum like you...
薄い望みにつられて
かき集められたクズどもが
Scum who are hanging to the last thread of hope,
地獄のふちをさまよう修羅の船
on board a ship sailing on the brink of hell...
The ship's name is Espoir.
その名はエスポワール　希望の船
The ship of hope.
決心は ついたかい？
Have you made up your mind?
２つ質問 いいすか？
May I ask two questions?
船でするギャンブルは
何かっていうことと
What type of gambling is involved?
負けたら強制労働って
言ってたけど
And upon losing, what type of forced labour...
...would the losers have to do?
何をやらされるんですか？
残念だが どっちも答えられない
Sorry but I can answer neither question.
- But...! - Well, listen up.
そんな…
まあ 聞け
If you are informed of what happens on board,
何をやるか教えちまったら
早い段階で参加を決めた奴に
有利になるだろう
won't those who joined earlier be at an advantage?
And about the conditions after losing,
あと負けた時の処遇だが
I am not clear on this matter at all.
この件に関しては
俺は よくは知らん
What? Not clear?
は？知らない？
だが心配することはねえ
But there's nothing to worry about.
このクルーズの目的は
The purpose of this cruise is to help those in debt to pay it off.
そもそも負債者の救済に
あるんだからな
Pay it off?
救済？
The sponsor of this cruise...
クルーズを企画し
スポンサーになってるのは
名前を聞けば誰でも知ってる
大手の某ファイナンス会社だ
...is a top finance company that everyone has heard of.
ｽﾎﾟﾝｻｰはこの船で儲けようなんて
ケチなことは考えていない
The sponsor's motive isn't selfish nor profit-oriented.
そのギャンブルはカジノで
行われているようなものではなく
Gambling on this ship is different from gambling in casinos.
あくまでも参加者同士の取り合い
It's more like a competition among the participants.
参加者同士？
- Among the participants? - Yeah.
そして その結果
毎回 半数は船を下りる
Thus, half of them get to leave the ship everytime.
半分も？
Half of them?!
勝てば借金がチャラ
これは文句なく救済だ
If you win, your debt is cleared.
The debt will be paid off with no questions asked.
借りに負けても 長い間
借金に縛られて暮らすより
Even if you lose, rather than living in debt,
you live a regulated life for one or two years...
１～２年 規律ある暮らしをし
集中的に返済して
...that focuses on paying off your debt.
借金から解放されたほうが
どれだけマシか
Isn't that a better way of being free from debt?
Don't you agree?
そうは思わんか？
まあ 確かに…
Well, it's true...
I think you're lucky to be able to go on this cruise.
俺はな お前がこのクルーズに
ぶち当たったってことは
ラッキーだったと思ってる
You feel like garbage everyday, don't you?
お前の毎日ってのは
ゴミって感じだろう
無気力で自堕落で非生産的…
Powerless, degraded and non-productive.
- Right?
だろ？
まあ…
- Well...
Do you know why you are like that now?
どうして今 そうなのか分かるか？
いや…
No.
It's because you don't have money.
金をつかんでないからだ
金？
- Money?
- Yeah.
ああ　金がないから
毎日がリアルじゃない
Because you're broke, your life doesn't feel real.
たとえばﾊﾞｽｹｯﾄﾎﾞｰﾙのゴールが
100メートル上空にあってみろ
Imagine a basketball hoop 100 meters in the sky.
No one will attempt a shot.
誰もボールを投げようとはしない
今のお前は その届かないゴールに
うんざりしてる
You are now frustrated at that unreachable hoop.
Everything you desire is behind the show window.
欲しいものがあっても
全部ショーウインドーの向こう側
お前には届かない
その買えないストレスが
You can't reach it.
And, the stress of having no spending power...
お前から覇気をなくし
まっすぐな気持ちを殺している
...makes you down-hearted and unmotivated.
You vandalise imported cars, don't you?
お前 外車にイタズラしてたろ
That is one of the typical symptoms.
あれなんか その典型的な表れ
外車が欲しいのに 自分のものに
しようと考えられない
You want an imported car, but can't imagine ever owning one.
ハナから諦め
ケチなイタズラをして満足してる
So, you give up and satisfy yourself with petty tricks.
If you had 10 million yen, would you do that?
お前 今 1000万あったら
あんなマネするか？
しないだろう
今回だってそうだよ
You wouldn't, right?
It's the same thing now.
これほどの救済策に
関心を示さない
You show no interest in this amazing repayment scheme.
負け癖がしみついてる証拠だ
It's proof that you're tied to a loser's mentality.
This cruise is a great chance to rid yourself of this mentality!
このｸﾙｰｽﾞはそんなお前の負け癖を
一掃するいいチャンスだ
Well, Kaiji? Win and be rich!
な カイジ　勝って大金をつかめ
人生を変えろ
Change your life!
兄貴　吉井さんからお電話です
Boss, telephone call from Mr. Yoshi.
Right.
Hello, Endou speaking.
はい 遠藤です
Yes.
確かに俺は 何というか
すげえ煮詰まってて…
It's true that I'm rather down in the dumps.
カイジ君　席 あと２つだわ
Mr. Kaiji.
- Only two places left.
このクルーズの席だよ
- What?
Seats remaining on the cruise.
I'm not the only one recruiting people, you know.
手配してんの
俺一人じゃねえからさ
はい 遠藤金融
Hello, Endou Finance.
２つ？あと２つ…
Two? Two more left?
そんなこと言われても…
But despite knowing that...
Mr. Kaiji.
カイジ君　残念
- Sorry.
They're taken.
なくなった
W-Wait a minute!
ちょ ちょっと待ってください
Is there anything you can do?
何とか… 何とかなりませんか？
What? Do you want to join?
何だ？お前 参加したいのか？
まあ どちらかというと…
Well, given the choices...
Honestly.
ったく 待ってろ
掛け合ってみる
Hang on, I'll try and ask.
お… お願いします
T-Thanks!
Mr. Yoshi, this is Endou.
ああ 吉井さん　遠藤ですが
Actually, about the event we were discussing...
実は例のアレなんですが
Yes... Yes. That's right.
ええ ええ… はい そうです
Please...
頼む
Done! They said they'd add another place.
ねじ込めた
席を１つ 増やしてくれるそうだ
Really?
ホントですか？
じゃあ
So, please sign and stamp your seal here.
早速だが これに署名と拇印を
So, Kaiji...
こうしてカイジ…
Thank you!
ご苦労さん
契約
Contract sealed!
見事にハマるもんすね
携帯１つで
People fall for it easily with just one phone call, eh?
Cornering a hesitant client.
迷ってる客を追い込む
不動産屋の常套手段さ
It's a typical sales technique in real estate.
こんな薄気味悪いクルーズが
引く手あまたなはずがねえだろが
No sane person would rush to join such a risky cruise.
どっちかっていうと 船から
下りられないクチでしょ あいつ
But somehow, that guy is likely to be unable to leave the ship.
そりゃ全然無理だろ　だってよ
That's a given fact.
He saw me as a good guy during my phone act...
さっき俺がクルーズにねじ込む
うそ電話してた時
...in trying to get him a place on the cruise.
あいつ たぶん俺のこと
いい人だと思ったはずだ
A good guy?
いい人… ですか？
ああいうバカがいるから
ヤクザは食いっぱぐれねえんだ
It's thanks to fools like him that the yakuza remain employed.
俺がいい人のわけ ねえじゃねえか
I can never be a good guy.
Idiots like that are only going to be eaten up...
あの船じゃ ああいうウスノロは
いのいちに餌食…
食い物にされるだけ
...like plenty of bait on the ship.
[One month later, Harumi Pier]
The participants arrived at different times,
参加者たちは時差をつけて
so as to avoid looking conspicuous.
目立たぬように招集された
まず ここでボディチェック
First, there's a body check here.
武器 危険物 携帯電話の有無を
確認される
The possession of weapons,
dangerous objects and mobile phones are checked for.
Of course, these are prohibited onboard.
むろん これらの持ち込みは
禁止である
それが済むと
本人かどうか今一度 確認
After that, they are checked to see if their identity matches.
And then they board.
そして乗船
Welcome.
どうぞ
何だよ こいつら
What's wrong with these guys?
どいつもこいつも
ﾏｲﾅｽのｵｰﾗに満ちてやがんの
Every single one of them looks hopeless.
Well, when up to one's neck in debt,
まあ うんざりするほど
借金抱えてるから無理もねえか
it's probably expected.
Sorry to have kept you waiting.
お待たせいたしました
早速ですが
Now, we will commence the lending of your war funds.
これから
軍資金の貸し付けを行います
The upper limit is 10 million, the lower limit is 1 million.
貸し付けの上限は1000万
下限は100万
In other words, everyone must borrow at least 1 million.
つまり すべての方に
最低100万は借りていただきます
金利は利率1.5％の10分複利
The interest is at 1.5% per 10 minutes.
クルーズは４時間の予定ですから
The cruise is booked for four hours, and...
借りた額に４割ほど上乗せして
返していただければ結構です
...so long you repay 40% above what you borrowed,
you are in the clear.
４割？
40%?
40%... What?! Are you kidding me?
４割とは何だ！ナメてんのか？
足元 見るのもいい加減にしろ
Stop taking advantage of us!
そうだよ　どこの世界に
10分複利なんて話があんだよ
Exactly! Whoever heard of an interest rate every 10 minutes?!
- That's right!
そうだ
ふざけるな
- Stop this!
どこまで搾り取るつもりだ
How much more do you want to exploit us?!
There's no such thing.
とんでもない
We are giving everyone here an unheard of chance...
我々は皆様に
借金 一括返済という
未曾有のチャンスを
与えているのです
...to repay all your debts.
それを考えれば
４割は非常にリーズナブル
Bearing that in mind, 40% is very reasonable.
This is a philanthropic rate.
良心的金利でございます
ふざけるな　俺たちみたいな
債務者から まだ取ろうってのか？
You can't be serious!
Do you still want to exploit even more out of us debtors?!
いい加減にしろ
That's enough!
あまりムチャ言うと
俺たちはみんな 下りるぞ
If you insist on this, we will get off right here!
どうぞ　引き止めはしません
Be my guest. We will not stop you.
下りて 借金を10年20年かけて
返すというのも
Getting off the ship and paying your debt in 10 or 20 years...
...is also a choice.
これまた１つの選択
どうぞ ご自由に
Please feel free to do so.
汚ねえ　俺たちはそういう選択が
できないからこそ
How despicable.
Aren't we on board this ship because we haven't any choice?
この船に乗ってるんじゃねえか
ええい クソ…
いかがなさいますか 石田様
Darn it!
So what do you say, Mr. Ishida?
100万だ　クソッ
Give me 1 million!
Darn it!
ありがとうございます
Thank you very much.
次の方 どうぞ
Next, please.
沢村 100
中根 100万
Sawamura, 1 million!
Nakane, 1 million!
There's no need to even ask.
聞くまでもねえ
皆 下限の100に決まってる
Everyone will borrow the lower limit of 1 million.
何であいつらのために 高い金利
出して金を借りる必要がある
Why borrow a larger sum at such high interest?
ふざけるな
What crooks!
どいつもこいつも
何をやるか分からんちゅうに
When no one even knows what we're going to have to do...
アホちゃうか？
Are you guys stupid or what?
Funai.
船井や
上限いっぱい
Give me the upper limit.
いけねえ　俺 寝ぼけてやがる
同情してどうする
This is not good... I must be daydreaming.
Why am I sympathising with them?
今は自分が勝つことだけを
考えりゃいい
I just have to think about winning for myself!
Just think about winning.
勝つことだけ…
あの男の言うとおりだ
Just like that guy said,
we don't know what we'll be made to do.
俺たちは まだ何をやるか
知らされてない
ギャンブルを打つ者にとって
金は寿命
A gambler's life is measured in cash.
次の方
Next.
伊藤カイジ　1000万
Ito Kaiji. 10 million.
軍資金の貸し付けを終えると
After the lending,
大金を借りた者のみ
ホルスターを手渡される
those who borrowed large amounts are given a holster.
これは現金を上着の内側に
しまえるようにという
This is a consideration by the organisation for the participants,
主催者側の配慮
to place their money inside their jackets.
After that, the participants will wear...
その後 上着の左胸に
マジックテープを付けられ
...magic tape on the left side of their jackets...
...and given envelopes A and B.
紙袋Ａ Ｂを渡される
動きだした
The ship's moving off.
埠頭を離れたんだ
We have left the pier.
もう引き返せない
There's no turning back.
プレイルームに案内された
参加者を前に
The participants are led to the play room,
ホールマスター 利根川の
ギャンブルの説明が始まる
...and the gambling rules are explained...
...to them by the hall master, Tonegawa.
説明は ただ一度のみ
繰り返しません
I will only explain once without repeating.
後で質問されても
お答えしかねますので
We might be unable to answer you later,
どうか集中力をもって
お聞きください
so please concentrate and listen carefully.
では入場の際 手渡された
Ａの袋を開封してください
Now, please open the envelope marked "A"...
...which you were handed upon entry here.
それが今夜 皆様の命運を握る
ギャンブルの種目
That is the gambling event that will determine the destiny...
...of everyone present here.
No way! This is just...
バカな　だってこれ…
これは…
This is...
カードの図案を見れば
ゲームは一目瞭然
From the card diagrams, it's obvious what the game is about.
ただし 通常のやり方と違い
However, this is different from the usual method.
グー チョキ パーを
無制限に出すことは許されません
You aren't allowed unrestricted use of Rock, Paper and Scissors.
使えるカードは与えられた
グー チョキ パー
You're given four of each kind, and you may use...
それぞれ４枚
計12枚のカードのみ
...each of the 12 cards once.
言うなら 限定ジャンケン
In other words, this is Restricted Rock Paper Scissors.
希望の船 エスポワール
The ship of hope, Espoir.
カイジたちの命運を賭けた
果てなき航海が
The voyage on which Kaiji will bet his destiny has just begun.
今 始まる
次回｢火蓋｣
Next, Open Fire.